# Dr. Ana Karen Velázquez Sánchez



28.09.1989, Mexico

(+49) 1774694088

Lübecker Str. 102

### **LANGUAGES**

o Spanish Native

o English Proficient, Toefl iBT o German Intermediate, B1.1 Carl Duisberg

o Japanese Novice, A1.1 Hamburger Volkshochschule

#### AWARDS AND FELLOWSHIPS

o Fellowship Doctoral studies

Fellowship Master studies

International Genetically Engineered Machine Competition (iGEM 2019) – Team Hamburg gold

#### TRAINING AND WORKSHOPS

Mathematics of life: modelling molecular mechanisms 202

PIER Startup Bootcamp I: "Design Thinking"

 Young Entrepreneur in Science: From Potential to Prototype

'From PhD to Innovator'

#### **INTERESTS**

Multidisciplinary research

Synthetic biology ,biomedicine, RNA therapeutics Artificial intelligence and machine learning

Sailing and music

Due to my Ph.D. studies, in addition to my computer science qualifications, I have acquired molecular biology knowledge, laboratory/experimental skills, and modeling and simulating molecular mechanisms. I have experienced the systems development cycle, including quality assurance, using a range of programming languages and development tools. Specializing in synthetic and systems biology, passionate about multidisciplinary projects and learning.

#### **EDUCATION**

o Doktorin der Naturwissenschaften with honors (1.0, magna cum laude) Oct 2017 - Dec 2021 Hamburg University of Technology (TUHH) co-affiliated with Hamburg University (UHH). Germany. Dissertation: "Design and implementation of molecular circuits for mitigating genetic diseases"

Master of Science in Computer Science

Oct 2012 - Oct 2014

Center for Scientific Research and Higher Education at Ensenada (CICESE). Mexico.

Dissertation: "Logic gates based on DNA strand displacement"

o Bachelor of Computer Science

Aug 2007 - Oct 2012

Autonomous University of Baja California (UABC). Mexico.

#### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

Postdoctoral associate (synthetic and systems biology)

Jan 2022 - Dec 2022

AG Ignatova, Hamburg University (UHH). Germany.

Tasks: experimental research, mathematical modeling, and simulations, data analysis, generating plots and images, preparing manuscripts for publication, teaching

Guest Research Scientist (PhD student)

Oct 2017 - Dec 2021

Algebraic Engineering Group, Institute of Embedded Systems (TUHH) and AG Ignatova, Hamburg University (UH). Germany.

Tasks: research and development of molecular circuits toward the mitigation of genetic diseases, kinetic modeling, simulations, and experimental research.

o Scientific applications software developer

Jan 2015 - Jul 2017

The Gulf of Mexico Research Consortium (CIGoM). Mexico.

Project "Data base and management system for oceanographic expeditions"

Tasks: Development of data management platform for multidisciplinary scientific data

Research assistant

Nov 2014 - Dec 2015

Center for Scientific Research and Higher Education at Ensenada (CICESE). Mexico.

Project "Cellular computation models and their application to the design of biomolecular logic circuits" Tasks: Development of full adder based on DNA strand displacement

o Internship in Software Quality Assurance (SQA)

Dec 2010- Dec 2011

Navico Marine Electronics R&D. Mexico.

Project "Reengineering process: tracking of software defects"

Tasks: Software testing and issue tracking, scripting for automation of test cases

o Working student: Ambient Intelligence App developer and trainer Aug 2010 - Dec 2010 Autonomous University of Baja California (UABC). Mexico.

Projects "Development of Applications on Ambient Intelligence in Support of Non-pharmacological Treatment of the Elderly" and "Introduction to informatics and media for senior adults'

Tasks: Development of Serious games on tactile surfaces, production of teaching/didactic materials for the course, and course trainer.

#### **SKILLS**

#### Programming, software, and libraries

- o Programming languages: Python, R, Java, C#, Matlab, HTML5, CSS, JavaScript, PHP, SQL, C++
- o Figure preparation: Photoshop
- o Molecular thermodynamics prediction: ViennaRNA, NUPACK
- o Molecular simulations: COPASI, VisualDSD, SimBiology
- o Graphs and plots: Ggplot2, matplotlib, Seaborn,
- o Web development: Laravel, Bootstrap, October CMS, Jquery
- o Formats: XML, SBOL
- SQA: Jvra
- Text processing: LaTex, Microsoft Office

#### Molecular biology lab techniques

- Fluorescence activated cell sorting (FACS) o Microbiology, e.g. culture, golden gate assembly (GGA) cloning, DNA/RNA extraction
- o Microplate assays
- o RNA isolation and northern dot blots
- o PCR (RT-PCR)
- Electrophoresis (e.g. SDS-page)

#### General

- Coding and computer skills
- Data analysis and design
- International work experience
- Writing and communication (scientific articles writing, scientific talks, workshop organization, teaching)
- o Problem-solving, attention to detail, critical thinking, fast learning
- o Organization (e.g. project planning and management, workshop organization) and creativity (e.g. figures and data representation)

## **REFERENCES**

- Prof. Dr. Zoya Ignatova, Group Leader AG Ignatova Lab (UHH) zoya.ignatova@uni-hamburg.de
- Prof. Dr. Dr. habil. Karl-Heinz Zimmermann, Group Leader Algebraic Engineering (TUHH) k.zimmermann@tuhh.de